When developing learning algorithms, very
当开发学习算法时
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
often a few simple plots
往往几个简单的图
can give you a better
可以让你更好地
sense of what the algorithm
理解算法的内容
is doing and just sanity check
并且可以完整地检查下
that everything is going okay
算法是否正常运行
and the algorithms doing what is supposed to.
是否达到了算法的目的
For example, in an earlier
例如在之前的
video, I talked about how
视频中  我谈到了
plotting the cost function J
绘制成本函数J(θ)
of theta can help you
可以帮助
make sure that gradient descent is converging.
确认梯度下降算法是否收敛
Often, plots of the data
通常情况下  绘制数据
or of all the learning algorithm outputs
或学习算法所有输出
will also give you ideas
也会启发你
for how to improve your learning algorithm.
如何改进你的学习算法
Fortunately, Octave has very
幸运的是  Octave有非常
simple tools to generate lots
简单的工具用来生成大量
of different plots and when
不同的图
I use learning algorithms, I find
当我用学习算法时 我发现
that plotting the data, plotting
绘制数据
the learning algorithm and so
绘制学习算法等
on are often an important
往往是
part of how I get
我获得想法
ideas for improving the
来改进算法的重要部分
algorithms and in this video,
在这段视频中
I'd like to show you some
我想告诉你一些
of these Octave tools for plotting and visualizing your data.
Octave的工具来绘制和可视化你的数据
Here's my Octave window.
这是我的Octave窗口
Let's quickly generate some data
我们先来快速生成一些数据
for us to plot.
用来绘图
So I'm going to set T
我先设置t
to be equal to, you know, this array of numbers.
等于这个数列
Here's T, set of
这是t
numbers going from 0 up to .98.
是从0到0.98的集合
Let's set y1 equals sine
让我们设置y1等于sin
of 2 pie 40 and
2*pi*4*t （此处pi表示π）
if I want to plot the sine function, it's very easy.
如果我想绘制正弦函数 这是很容易的
I just type plot T comma Y
我只需要输入plot(t, y1)
1 and hit enter.
并回车
And up comes this plot
就出现了这个图
where the horizontal axis is
横轴是
the T variable and the vertical
t变量 纵轴是y1
axis is y1, which
也就是我们
is the sine you saw in the function that we just computed.
刚刚所输出的正弦函数
Let's set y2 to be
让我们设置y2
equal to the cosine
等于cos
of two pi, four T, like so.
2*pi*4*t
And if I plot
而如果我输入plot
T comma y2, what octave
t逗号y2
will I do is I'll take my
Octave将会
sine plot and it
消除之前的正弦图
will replace with this cosine
并且用这个余弦图来代替它
function and now, you know, cosine of xi of 1.
这里纵轴cos(x)从1开始
Now, what if I
如果我
want to have both
要同时表示
the sine and the cosine plots on top of each other?
正弦和余弦曲线
What I'm going to do is I'm
我要做的就是
going to type plot t,y1.
输入plot(t, y1)
So here's my sine function, and then
这是我的正弦函数
I'm going to use the function hold on.
我使用函数hold on
And what hold does it closes
hold on函数
octaves to now
的功能是将
figures on top of the
新的图像绘制在
old one and let
旧的之上
me now plot t y2.
我现在绘制t y2
I'm going to plot the cosine function in a different color.
我要以不同的颜色绘制余弦函数
So, let me put there
所以我在这里输入
r in quotation marks there
带引号的r
and instead of replacing
我将绘制余弦函数
the current figure, I'll plot the
在这之上
cosine function on top and
而不是替换了现有的图
the r indicates the what is an event color.
r表示所使用的颜色
And here additional commands - x
再加上命令xlabel('time')
label times, to label the X axis, or the horizontal axis.
来标记X轴即水平轴
And Y label values A,
输入ylabel('value')
to label the vertical axis value,
来标记垂直轴的值
and I can also
同时我也可以
label my two lines
来标记我的两条函数曲线
with this command: legend sine cosine
用这个命令 legend('sin', 'cos')
and this puts this
将这个
legend up on the upper
图例放在右上方
right showing what the 2
表示这两条曲线表示的内容
lines are, and finally title
最后输入title('myplot')
my plot is the title at the top of this figure.
在图像的顶部显示这幅图的标题
Lastly, if you want to save
如??果你想保存
this figure, you type print -dpng
这幅图像，你输入print -dpng
myplot
'myplot.png'
.png.
png是一个图像
So PNG is a graphics
文件格式
file format, and if you
如果你
do this it will let you save this as a file.
这样做了 它可以让你保存为一个文件
If I do that,
如果我这样做
let me actually change directory to,
让我先改一下路径
let's see, like
像这样
that, and then I will print that out.
然后我将它打出来
So this will take a
这需要一点时间
while depending on how
而这取决于你的
your Octave configuration is setup,
Octave的配置设置
may take a few seconds, but change
可能需要几秒钟  但改变
directory to my desktop and Octave
路径到我的桌面
is now taking a few seconds to save this.
现在Octave需要几秒钟??的时间来保存它
If I now go to my desktop, Let's hide these windows.
如果我现在去到我的桌面  先最小化这些窗口
Here's myplot.png
这就是
which Octave has saved, and you
Octave所保存的myplot.png
know, there's the figure saved as the PNG file.
这就是保存为PNG的文件
Octave can save thousand other formats as well.
Octave也可以保存为很多其他的格式
So, you can type help plot,
你可以键入help  plot
if you want to see the
如果你想试试
other file formats, rather than
其他格式的文件  而不是
PNG, that you can save
PNG 你可以把图片
figures in.
保存为其他格式
And lastly, if you want
最后如??果你想
to get rid of the plot, the
删掉这个图像
close command causes the figure to go away.
命令close会让这个图像关掉
As I figure if I type
如果我键入
close, that figure just
close  这个图像
disappeared from my desktop.
就从我的桌面消失了
Octave also lets you specify a figure and numbers.
Octave也可以让你为图像标号
You type figure 1 plots t, y1.
你键入figure(1); plot(t, y1);
That starts up
将显示
first figure, and that plots t, y1.
第一张图 绘制了变量t y1
And then if you want a second figure, you specify a different figure number.
如果你想绘制第二个图 你可以指定一个不同的数字编号
So figure two, plot t,
键入figure(2); plot(t, y2);
y2 like so, and
正如这样
now on my desktop, I actually have 2 figures.
现在我的桌面上  其实有2个图
So, figure 1 and figure
图1和图2
2 thus 1 plotting the sine
此时一个绘制正弦
function, 1 plotting the cosine function.
函数  另一个绘制了余弦函数
Here's one other neat command that
这是另一个我经常使用的命令
I often use, which is the subplot command.
subplot命令
So, we're going to use subplot 1 2 1.
我们要使用subplot(1,2,1)
What it does it sub-divides
它将图像
the plot into a
分为一个
one-by-two grid with the
1*2的格子
first 2 parameters are, and
也就是前两个参数
it starts to access the
然后它使用
first element. That's
第一个格子
what the final parameter 1 is, right?
也就是最后一个参数1的意思
So, divide my figure into a
所以，将我的图像分成
one by two grid, and I
1*2的格子
want to access the first
我现在使用
element right now.
第一个格子
And so, if I type that
如果我键入这个
in, this product, this figure, is on the left.
那么这个图像显示在左边
And if I plot t,
如果键入plot(t, y1)
y1, it now fills
现在这个图
up this first element.
显示在第一个格子
And if I I'll do subplot 122.
如果我键入subplot(1,2,2)
I'm going to start to
那么我就要
access the second element and plot t, y2.
使用第二个格子  键入plot(t, y2);
Well, throw in y2 in
现在y2显示在右边
the right hand side, or in the second element.
也就是第二个格子
And last command, you can
最后一个命令  你可以
also change the axis scales
改变轴的刻度
and change axis these to 1.51
比如改成
minus 1 1 and this
[0.5 1 -1 1]
sets the x range
也就是设置了
and y range for the
右边图的x轴
figure on the right,
和y轴的范围
and concretely, it assess the horizontal
具体而言 它将
major values in the figure
右图中的横轴
on the right to make sure 0.5
的范围调整至0.5到1
to 1, and the vertical
竖轴的范围为
axis values use the range from minus one to one.
-1到1
And, you know, you don't need to memorize all these commands.
而且 你不需要记住所有这些命令
If you ever need to
如果你需要
change the access or you
改变坐标轴或者
need to know is that, you know, there's an
需要知道axis命令
access command and you can
你可以
already get the details
用Octave中
from the usual octave help command.
help命令了解细节
Finally, just a couple last
最后  还有几个命令
commands CLF clear is
clf清除
a figure and here's one unique trait.
一幅图像 这里有一个独特的特点
Let's set a to be equal
让我们设置A等于
to a 5 by 5
一个5×5
magic squares a. So, a
magic方阵
is now this 5 by 5
现在A是这个5*5
matrix does a neat
的矩阵
trick that I sometimes use to
我有时用一个巧妙的方法
visualize the matrix, which is
来可视化矩阵
I can use image sc
也就是imagesc(A)
of a what this will
它将会
do is plot a five
绘制一个5*5的矩阵
by five matrix, a five by five grid of color.
一个5*5的彩色格图
where the different colors correspond to
不同的颜色对应
the different values in the A matrix.
A矩阵中的不同值
So concretely, I can also do color bar.
具体地说 我还可以使用函数colorbar
Let me use a
让我用一个
more sophisticated command, and image sc
更复杂的命令 imagesc(A)
A color bar
colorbar
color map gray.
colormap gray
This is actually running three commands at a time.
这实际上是在同一时间运行三个命令
I'm running image sc then running
运行imagesc然后运行
color bar, then running color map gray.
colorbar 然后运行colormap gray
And what this does, is it sets
它生成了
a color map, so a
一个颜色图像
gray color map, and on the
一个灰度分布图 并在
right it also puts in this color bar.
右边也加入一个颜色条
And so this color bar
所以这个颜色条
shows what the different shades of color correspond to.
显示不同深浅的颜色所对应的值
Concretely, the upper left
具体地  左上
element of the A matrix
A矩阵的元素
is 17, and so that corresponds
是17  所以对应
to kind of a mint shade of gray.
的是这样中等的灰度
Whereas in contrast the second
而与此相反的第二个
element of A--sort of the
元素  也就是
1 2 element of A--is 24.
A(1,2)元素
Right, so it's A 1 2 is 24.
代表的值为24
So that corresponds to
它对应于
this square out here, which is
这里的这个方块
nearly a shade of white.
是接近白色的灰度
And the small value, say
较小的值比如
A--what is that? A
A多少呢
4 5, you know, is a value
A(4,5)
3 over here that corresponds--
为3对应着
you can see on my color bar
你可以看到在我的颜色条
that it corresponds to a
它对应于
much darker shade in this image.
一个更暗的灰度
So here's another example,
这里是另一个例子
I can plot a larger, you
我可以绘制一个较大的
know, here's a magic 15 that
比如magic（15）
gives you a 15 by 15
给你一个15* 15
magic square and this
magic方阵
gives me a plot of what
这将会是一幅
my 15 by 15 magic squares values looks like.
15*15的magic方阵值的图
And finally to wrap
最后
up this video, what you've
总结一下这段视频
seen me do here is
你看到我所做的
use comma chaining of function calls.
是使用逗号连接函数调用
Here's how you actually do this.
这里是你如何真正做到这一点
If I type A equals
如果我键入a=1
1, B equals 2, C equals
b=2 c=3
3, and hit Enter, then
然后按Enter键
this is actually carrying out
其实这是将这
three commands at the same time.
三个命令同时执行
Or really carrying out three
或者是
commands, one after another,
将三个命令一个接一个执行
and it prints out all three results.
它将输出所有这三个结果
And this is a lot like
这很像
A equals 1, B equals
a=1; b=2;
2, C equals 3, except
c=3;
that if I use semicolons instead
如果我用分号来代替逗号
of a comma, it doesn't print out anything.
没有输出出任何东西
So, this, you know,
所以你知道
this thing here we call comma
这里我们称之为
chaining of commands, or comma chaining of function calls.
逗号连接的命令或函数调用
And, it's just another
只是另一种
convenient way in Octave to
Octave中更便捷的方式
put multiple commands like image sc
将多条命令例如imagesc
color bar, colon map
colorbar colormap
to put multi-commands on the same line.
将这多条命令写在同一行中
So, that's it.
所以 就是这样
You now know how to plot
现在你知道如何绘制
different figures and octave, and
Octave中不同的图像
in next video the
在下面的视频中
next main piece that I want
下一个主要内容
to tell you about is how to
我将告诉你怎样在Octave中
write control statements like if,
写控制语句 比如if
while, for statements and
while for语句
octave as well as hard to define and use functions
并且定义和使用函数